( Shindo Kaneto ) This is the susuki grass .
This place was difficult to find .
First we went to Adachigahara ,
where there is a legend of a she-demon ,
but the area had been developed .
One of the assistant directors
travelled right around Mt . Fuji looking for a place ,
but the grass fields were either being used by the military
or had been split up .
He finally decided to look near the marshes ,
and went to Inbanuma in Chiba where he found this place .
He wanted me to take a look ,
so I went to see .
It was just what we were looking for ,
so we decided to film there .
We had problems later with the stones and the bogs ,
but I didn 't see any of that then .
I just saw the grass rustling in the wind and thought , " This is perfect . "
Ever since we made Ningen ,
we 'd always lodged together when filming ,
but there was no suitable place to stay nearby ,
so we decided to build
a prefabricated house at the site .
The susuki grass is like having a black background .
There is nothing to get in the way .
It also provides a symbolic setting
for the Civil War period ,
and I wanted the grass swaying in the wind
to express the psychological nature of the film .
We were also working to a small budget ,
so we needed to use the minimum number of people
and this place was perfect for that .
( Sato Kei ) I hear the production budget was 15 million yen . Is that right ?
( Shindo ) About that .
In today 's terms , that 's about 300 million yen .
That 's Kaji Kentaro .
( Yoshimura Jitsuko ) They 're father and son , aren 't they ?
( Shindo ) Yes . That 's his son-in-law .
( Yoshimura ) The susuki grass is beautiful
and it 's very effective ,
psychologically .
( Shindo ) Okamoto Taro also said
that the grass made a fine background .
I 'm glad that we decided to use the grass fields ,
but it made filming very difficult .
( Sato ) I read the production notes again the other day .
They say how you had a flash of inspiration
about the hole which helped you to write the script .
( Shindo ) I felt that the hole signifies
the process by which people survived .
History tells us that
during the Civil War period
the civilian population clung on precariously
at the edge of existence ,
which means that we are here today
because they managed to survive .
It shows the strength of the people
at the bottom of the social heap .
I thought of depicting the harsh everyday life
of people who put
food on their plates
by murdering others .
I don 't mean that the hole is connected directly to this in any way ,
but I wanted to use it as a metaphor
for this way of survival .
( Sato ) The hole was like a disused well , wasn 't it ?
( Shindo ) Yes .
How old were you when you made this , Jitsuko ?
( Yoshimura ) I think I was about 19 .
( Shindo ) You were brimming with vitality then .
( Yoshimura ) It was only my third film . I didn 't know anything .
( Sato ) You look as fresh as a daisy .
( Yoshimura ) I watched the film the other day after many years ,
I really enjoyed it .
The clothes we wore in the film were supposed
to have been stolen , too .
You gave us two sets of clothes
and asked us to make sure they looked old ,
so I slept in mine .
I expect Nobuko did the same .
( Shindo ) The clothes were linen ,
I designed them myself .
( Yoshimura ) Really ?
( Shindo ) And I had them dyed .
Nobuko 's outfit had a crab design .
( Yoshimura ) Mine was a fan motif .
That was almost 40 years ago .
I 've forgotten so much .
( Shindo ) The reason the film is still so clear
is because it was shot in black and white .
If it had been colour , the colour would have faded by now .
( Yoshimura ) In black and white ,
it 's more impressive .
( Shindo ) I 'm still nostalgic about black and white now .
When they invented film ,
they couldn 't do colour at first ,
so they started with black and white .
But there are actually seven shades of grey in black and white .
It represents colour in the same way
as an Indian ink drawing .
It has that depth .
( Sato ) It is much better than badly used colour .
The susuki grass , too .
( Yoshimura ) Absolutely .
( Sato ) It stirs the imagination . ( Yoshimura ) That 's right .
( Shindo ) In that sense , black and white is superior .
It should have been
invented after colour .
All you have to do with colour is film it as it is .
We built this set ourselves .
( Sato ) It was tough for the assistant directors .
( Shindo ) They had it tough .
They were covered in cuts and bruises .
We had eight assistant directors .
There are usually four .
We wanted them to gain
a wide range of experience .
We were an independent production company ,
so we didn 't rely on any outside people .
We wanted to do everything ourselves .
That 's how we did things .
( Yoshimura ) Eight ads ?
( Shindo ) That 's right .
( Sato ) Some were straight out of university , weren 't they ?
( Shindo ) Some out of university , some were amateurs , some were veterans .
They were all mixed together .
It was an interesting blend .
We did everything there on location .
It all took time and effort .
( Sato ) If I remember right ,
you used about 30 kilowatts of lighting .
( Shindo ) That 's right . We used about 30 kilowatts .
We didn 't use lights in the day .
Just when we filmed
in the evening or in the morning .
( Sato ) Living on location gave you plenty of time .
You could be very flexible .
You could snatch a single cut
when the wind or the light was just right .
( Shindo ) That 's right .
It was like living and sleeping on the set .
We could be very versatile .
It 's an interesting way of doing things ,
but it 's stressful because you 're shut in .
But when you have a job to do , I think it 's best
to keep people captive at the place they 're working .
( Yoshimura ) Oh , really ?
( Shindo ) If you don 't do that , people can 't commit themselves .
I think everyone wants to be kept captive ,
so that they can get on with their work .
( Yoshimura ) I think it 's only you who thinks that .
We got to go to Tokyo once every three weeks .
( Yoshimura ) Or was it every two weeks ? ( Shindo ) Every three weeks .
( Yoshimura ) One thing I remember clearly
is that you didn 't go back to Tokyo at all .
Why was that ?
( Shindo ) I wanted to stay at the location continuously .
I felt that I needed to stay there
to maintain my feel for the place .
( Yoshimura ) Really ? I didn 't know what you were thinking .
I just thought , " Yahoo , a holiday ! "
I think it was two days and one night .
I was so happy .
I suppose there were taxis , but ...
You wouldn 't have got taxis out there .
We all piled into two trucks .
It was about 10 minutes to the station , wasn 't it ?
( Shindo ) It was four kilometres . So it was about 10 minutes .
( Yoshimura ) We went to the station to catch the train to Tokyo .
We were all so excited .
We stayed one night and then came back the next evening .
We arrived at the station and the trucks were waiting for us .
Then it was back to work .
( Shindo ) This is a canal , but it looks like
a continental river because there 's no flow .
( Yoshimura ) It was beautiful . ( Sato ) It 's man-made .
It was built to take
the overflow from the marshes down to the river .
( Shindo ) There 's a dam a little further along .
This is where Kei appears .
The reason I made him a monk
was that he wouldn 't have to wear a wig .
It would just appear that his hair had grown .
( Yoshimura ) You were lucky , Kei .
( Sato ) And the clothes would have kept me safe .
( Shindo ) That 's right .
With monk 's clothes ,
he would have been safe on the road .
( Yoshimura ) Nobuko and I both wore wigs .
( Shindo ) But it was mostly your own hair .
We just added a little .
It was hard work rigging the lighting here because the roof was so low . @ @ až sem pøeèteno
( Sato ) It caught fire once . That 's right .
You were the first one to escape when the fire started , Jitsuko .
( Yoshimura ) Was I really ?
( Sato ) You were the first out of the door . ( Yoshimura ) Because I was young !
( Shindo ) It was hard going for everyone .
But because you were all held captive in one place ,
there was nowhere to escape to and we had plenty of time .
( Yoshimura ) Yes , we had lots of time .
( Shindo ) Because we had so much time ,
it felt as if we could be relaxed about things . Mind you , it was hot .
( Sato ) God , it was hot !
( Shindo ) Not only that ...
The reeds and the scenery may look cool ,
but the hot , stifling smell of the grass was terrible .
I remember Kei saying that
we ran the risk of catching a nasty disease from the mites
if we filmed there .
We were lucky though ,
because no one got sick .
( Sato ) When Masaki Kobayashi was filming The Human Condition ,
up in Sarobetsu in Hokkaido ,
the locals warned him about the danger of disease from mites .
When they had to go into the swamp ,
they wrapped themselves in plastic underneath their clothes .
They were worried , but they didn 't catch anything .
( Shindo ) It would have been quite natural to get sick in a place like that .
( Sato ) That 's right .
I didn 't know about it until later ,
but the area where the marsh meets the reed beds
is a very primitive environment .
It was like that tens of thousands of years ago .
It looks as if you could walk along quite easily ,
but it 's so boggy you would sink in up to your waist .
( Sato ) Does it belong to the Water Agency ?
( Shindo ) Yes , it 's managed by the Water Agency .
We got permission to use it ,
and we built the set there .
Because we did it here , we didn 't have to worry about onlookers .
We basically had a cast of three .
It was good because we could focus that way .
You wouldn 't have been able to appear in anything else ,
with a beard like that anyway .
It was lucky for us .
Mind you , it was rough for the actors , wasn 't it ?
( Sato ) I wasn 't much in demand anyway .
( Shindo ) That 's not true .
( Sato ) I arrived at the set about one week
after shooting had started .
There was a bath and a toilet by then .
( Yoshimura ) There were separate toilets for men and women .
( Sato ) I remember these small , yellow
poisonous moths appeared once .
One of the crew was sitting in the bath
with a rash all over his body .
( Shindo ) Talk about moths to the flame .
The insects would emerge in swarms in the evening .
( Sato ) It was amazing .
( Shindo ) I thought there were only
one or two types of insect that come out at night ,
but there were scores of different types .
( Yoshimura ) Were there that many ?
( Shindo ) One type would arrive en masse ,
stay for a week and then disappear .
Then a different type would turn up .
The insects were terrible . They would drop to the floor ,
and the crawfish would come to eat them .
( Sato ) We used a light trap and caught hundreds of them .
( Shindo ) They came pouring in and dropped down dead .
( Sato ) We burnt them all with gasoline . It was crazy .
When we filmed at night , the insects would come
flying into your mouth when you tried to say your lines .
( Shindo ) That 's right .
But the daytime was a hard grind , too .
( Sato ) The ADs had it tough .
( Shindo ) There wasn 't much to do at night ,
so we passed the time cremating insects .
( Sato ) You would go to bed early because you don 't drink .
But a few of us would sit out on the embankment ,
drinking till midnight .
( Yoshimura ) You drank on the embankment ? I didn 't know that .
( Sato ) If we had sat outside , it would have been too noisy .
( Shindo ) It 's slightly cooler out there by the river , too .
Sitting and drinking on the riverbank .
It 's not something you get to do every day .
( Yoshimura ) It was a priceless experience .
( Shindo ) If we 'd had the money ,
we could have provided all sorts of facilities ,
but I think it was better this way .
This sort of primitive style is better , isn 't it ?
( Sato ) I think so .
( Shindo ) Our primitive lifestyle matched the film itself .
Simple food and cheap dried fish .
You 'd think we 'd have all kinds of fresh fish ,
staying next to a swamp .
But we didn 't .
( Sato ) There were grass carp .
( Yoshimura ) Were they big ? ( Sato ) About one metre long .
( Shindo ) Grass carp were introduced from China .
There were snakehead mullet , too .
They can actually come onto the land for a while .
They look a bit like snakes .
( Sato ) The grass carp ate up all the small fish in the area .
They built a fish pen for them on the bank ,
but they were still wiped out .
( Shindo ) They caught the small fish and put them in a fish pen .
Didn 't you have moxibustion treatment on your stomach
to increase your weight when we were doing Ningen , Kei ?
You have plenty of meat on you here .
( Sato ) Ningen was two years before this .
I only weighed 48 kg at the time .
After six months of treatment , I was up to 73 kg .
Onibaba was only two years after that .
( Shindo ) You were a bit chubby then . ( Sato ) I 'd lost a bit of weight then .
I was about 70 kg here .
( Shindo ) Yes , I thought you were quite big then .
( Yoshimura ) Is that a snakehead mullet you 're holding ?
( Shindo ) No , it 's a crucian carp . ( Sato ) A big one .
There wouldn 't have been any grass carp or snakehead mullet
in those days .
They were only introduced after the war .
( Shindo ) 19 years old ? You 're just brimming with youth .
( Sato ) Your skin is glowing .
( Yoshimura ) I watched the film again a few days ago ,
I could hardly believe I was so young once . It made me happy to see .
( Shindo ) Of course . That 's natural .
The mud beneath the reeds was like a quagmire .
It was very unpleasant , but we were lucky
that no one got sick .
( Yoshimura ) We were very lucky .
( Sato ) We didn 't take any precautions either .
( Shindo ) We didn 't have any medical facilities .
( Shindo ) Our budget didn 't stretch to that .
( Yoshimura ) We didn 't have any inoculations .
( Sato ) We didn 't do anything like that .
( Shindo ) None of the ADs got sick either .
( Yoshimura ) That 's right .
( Shindo ) When the ADs got stressed out ,
they 'd run marathons to the railway station in the evening .
( Sato ) Did they do that ?
( Shindo ) They wanted to burn up their energy .
( Yoshimura ) I didn 't know that .
( Shindo ) The day after a holiday ,
I would sometimes go up and wait on the embankment
and would watch as people came trickling back in ones and twos .
I was relieved to see them .
They returned but they 'd been thinking .
( Sato ) Did you think they 'd escape ?
( Shindo ) Yes . I thought some people would run away .
( Yoshimura ) But no one did ? ( Shindo ) No one did .
Maybe they just didn 't have the time to think of escaping .
( Sato ) That was the year of the Tokyo Olympics .
Even when you got away to Tokyo , it was noisy and crowded .
( Shindo ) You don 't get many opportunities
for a group of people to focus
on a single task like this .
( Sato ) The samurai over there is Tanaka Hiroshi .
He became famous doing that ham commercial .
He was a stand-in for Mifune , wasn 't he ?
It was the boneless ham .
( Shindo ) He 's actually quite small , but he 's wearing armour .
It 's not funny ,
but he almost drowned .
I could have filmed the scene in separate cuts ,
but I wanted to film the whole scene to give it power .
That 's why we did it this way .
That 's how we did it , but it was serious .
( Sato ) I was really worried .
( Shindo ) You were impatient . ( Sato ) No , I was worried !
( Shindo ) In the film , I mean .
You were impatient , waiting for him to arrive .
You spear him here .
( Yoshimura ) After all that effort to swim across ...
( Sato ) The water was dirty .
( Shindo ) It looks clean , but it was dirty .
( Sato ) That 's Yamaguchi .
Tanaka was Terajima Mitsugu 's son , wasn 't he ?
( Shindo ) I think he was related to the wife of the cameraman .
That 's how he came to be with us .
I used him because he also did some stunt work .
There was no point in rehearsing this .
They just had to react as they went along .
They turned this into a ballet in America .
An American production company
is interested in buying the story .
It 's a simple story .
It 's a very traditional folk tale ,
and this folk tale has
the man and woman relationship .
It 's simple .
( Sato ) It was about this time that Tonoyama stopped drinking .
( Shindo ) That 's right . He shouted out , " I 'm giving up drinking from today ! "
( Sato ) But nobody paid a blind bit of notice .
( Shindo ) Why did you used to call Tonoyama-san
by the nickname oyabin ?
( Sato ) It comes from the words oyabun meaning " boss "
and hagechabin meaning " baldy " .
( Yoshimura ) I worked with Tonoyama
on films after this .
He was very shy .
I remember if I teased him ,
he would just look down and grin sheepishly .
( Shindo ) He was a cultured man .
( Sato ) He was intelligent .
( Shindo ) Yes , and he was a humble man .
He was a cultured man and intelligent ,
and a funny person .
He was an interesting fellow .
( Yoshimura ) I think everybody had times
when they were stressed out
and wanted to go home .
I had that feeling at times ,
but Nobuko looked after me .
I can only remember the happy times now .
( Shindo ) You were young ,
and everyone was eager .
I just let people do their thing .
You were all enthusiastic .
( Yoshimura ) Did we rehearse ?
( Shindo ) No . ( Sato ) We just did a camera test .
( Yoshimura ) The set was only about five minutes from where we stayed .
I thought we did a bit of rehearsal ,
but it 's over thirty years ago and I can 't remember .
( Sato ) Maybe you did some practice by yourself .
( Yoshimura ) I wasn 't that serious .
( Shindo ) There was no point in rehearsal .
There 's no way to rehearse how to bite into a chunk of meat .
It wasn 't a specific type of acting .
We were portraying humans reduced
almost to the level of beasts .
There 's no way to rehearse that .
Simply staying in that place together
was a sufficient rehearsal .
( Yoshimura ) That feeling that we were all in it together
was very different from the two films I 'd done before that .
( Shindo ) I went to Montreal last year , 1999 ,
and screened Onibaba and The Naked Island .
The people I met in the cafés knew Onibaba .
When we met , they would all say , " Ah , Onibaba , Onibaba ! "
You could hear them , " Onibaba , Onibaba . "
It 's very simple and straightforward ,
and people overseas appreciated it as well .
( Sato ) It was very popular .
( Shindo ) " Onibaba , Onibaba , " they said !
I took four prints and they screened them two at a time
at the main venue .
Film made its appearance in the 20th century ,
and now you can see Nobuko like this ,
even though she 's no longer with us .
In some respect , the viewpoint of life and death has changed .
The voice remains .
( Yoshimura ) When I saw the titles at the beginning ,
I was shocked to think that so many of those people
have passed away .
We might be the only three left .
( Shindo ) Kuroda , the cameraman ,
the lighting man ,
Shige who did the make-up .
( Yoshimura ) Uno , Tonoyama , Tanaka
and Sonesho are all dead .
It 's just the three of us .
And you 're the fittest of us all .
( Shindo ) I think not . I 'm 89 years old .
( Sato ) How old were you when you made Onibaba ?
( Shindo ) Fifty-five .
I was fit then .
Breath is important
for acting and for directing .
If you have no breath
left in your lungs after you have breathed out ,
you lose your power .
When your breath is used up and doesn 't come out anymore ,
it is useless .
( Yoshimura ) You 've gone crazy here , Kei .
( Shindo ) The film doesn 't look at all dated .
( Yoshimura ) That 's right .
( Shindo ) I added the cooing of pigeons
to the scene when you are running .
I heard that pigeons are known for their fecundity ,
so I added the sound to the scene where Jitsuko
is running through the grass in the grip of desire .
I added it for effect .
( Yoshimura ) I didn 't know that .
( Shindo ) Hayashi Hikaru also came to the set .
( Yoshimura ) I ran like the wind then .
I was covered in scratches .
If I tried that now ,
I 'd have a heart attack .
( Shindo ) We could make it appear
to be night ,
because we filmed in black and white .
If you adjust the contrast ,
use a red filter
and emphasise the black ,
then you are able to turn day into night .
This technique was developed for black and white film .
I 'm not sure who invented it .
( Sato ) Can 't you do it with colour ? ( Shindo ) No , not with colour .
The picture would be dark .
It just becomes darker .
There 's an effect that occurs ...
If you increase the contrast in black and white film ,
it has the effect of accentuating the white ,
so the image becomes clearer .
The effect can be quite strange .
It 's very effective .
We filmed the susuki grass
with and without lights .
If the lights are switched on ,
the sky becomes dark
and the grass appears white .
Without light , the grass becomes black and the sky white .
The two can be used as a montage to create an interesting effect .
I took this shot at about 3.5 times speed .
They usually shoot running giraffes
and other animals at between
3.5 and 5 times normal speed .
From the start , I wanted the swaying of the susuki grass
to express the psychological nature of the film .
( Yoshimura ) Neither Nobuko nor I had names ,
but Hachi and my dead husband did .
( Shindo ) I used you as symbols .
( Yoshimura ) Why was that ?
( Shindo ) ... to represent people .
As a person who would be able
to represent the populace .
You can only get this kind of effect with black and white film .
We couldn 't film on cloudy days .
You don 't get the effect of black and white film
unless you have clear blue skies .
In the old days , we would wait for clear weather to film .
Nowadays you can get vivid colours regardless
of whether it 's cloudy or not .
There 's no need to fear the clouds ,
you can shoot to your heart 's content .
On the other side of the coin ,
people now take less care in composing their shots .
How long did you stay on location ?
( Sato ) Was it June we started ?
( Yoshimura ) I think I was there for three months .
( Shindo ) It took a long time ,
because we had to wait for the weather .
( Sato ) According to these records ,
filming started 30th June 1964 and I joined in July .
We finished up on 9th September .
Shindo , Kuroda and Shirota
left on the two o 'clock train
on 9 October .
It says that they departed under leaden skies with heavy hearts .
( Shindo ) Whenever I start a new project ,
it feels as if I 'm beginning a new life .
And when the time comes
when the work ends ,
it feels as if one life
has come to an end .
( Sato ) When an actor has played his part , he goes home .
When the soundman and other crew have done their jobs , they go home .
The director stays till the end .
( Shindo ) That 's right .
I suppose it 's mentally
and physically tiring .
But it 's the actors
who do the running
and all the director has to do
is watch them perform .
I admire actors .
( Yoshimura ) Thank you !
( Shindo ) Mind you , I suppose they do it
because it 's interesting ,
so I shouldn 't worry too much about them .
But actors are a breed apart .
( Sato ) I always have a bit
of a guilty conscience as an actor .
Whether it 's film or stage ,
the actor works to a script
and has someone to direct him ,
and yet he plays it as if it is all his own work .
It 's like he 's cheating the audience and the director .
( Yoshimura ) Because I 'm impudent , I don 't feel like that .
( Sato ) It 's shyness .
( Shindo ) I can understand that .
A director also has a feeling of impotence .
Because he doesn 't actually do it .
He orders people about , but doesn 't actually do it himself .
He leaves everything to other people .
It 's like there 's a glass wall
in front of you .
It 's frustrating .
( Sato ) Yes , it must be frustrating for a director .
Especially when the actors can 't get it right !
( Shindo ) No , it 's not that .
If the film turns out well , the director gets the credit ,
but he didn 't really do it himself .
It 's funny , when I speak to actors
who do stage work ,
they still find it interesting
even when they are performing the same role ,
day after day .
( Sato ) Not me .
I like a one-off performance .
I don 't mind rehearsing for two weeks
or a month .
That 's necessary to understand the script .
But I just want to do one performance .
( Shindo ) It 's a different audience every day .
( Sato ) That 's true .
But I like to do it just once .
( Shindo ) I 'm the same .
As a director , I only want to shoot a scene once .
I don 't want to go back and do it again .
It doesn 't work well if I do .
Even if you see something that 's not right
in the rushes and you decide to retake it ,
it 's not good enough .
If you retake it , it never looks right .
It 's as if you have painted over the top of it .
You need to start with a blank sheet .
It 's all or nothing .
( Sato ) First time is best for acting as well .
( Yoshimura ) There is a tension in it .
( Sato ) From the second try onward ,
you are aiming for safety .
( Shindo ) Actors are artists .
They are creative .
They create something from unknown spaces within ,
using their bodies
and their actions .
They work from morning to night ,
but that doesn 't mean they do it best
at the end of the day .
Mizoguchi Kenji said the same thing .
He would sometimes do test runs for a whole day ,
and he said that people often got worse the more they tried .
( Yoshimura ) Maybe because they were tired !
( Shindo ) We burned tyres to get the smoke here .
It was really hard work just getting over there to do it .
Not for me , but for the ADs !
We just watched it .
It was the little things like that which took time .
That 's why we were there three months .
For example , if a clump of reeds fell down ,
we would have to bring some more in and prop them up .
They look beautiful ,
but there are plenty of shots where we had to prop them up .
It was all hard work .
( Yoshimura ) The reeds were so high .
( Shindo ) They are about twice the height of a person .
These are reeds .
There were two types of reed ,
as well as the susuki grass .
( Yoshimura ) Someone said that it 's scary to run through
the susuki grass , but it wasn 't just grass .
There were reeds , too .
( Shindo ) We built a well in order to film ,
but it was destroyed
in the typhoon .
All kinds of things like that happened .
He 's imitating the barking of a dog .
( Yoshimura ) It 's so many years since I saw the film .
There were so many love scenes !
( Sato ) It 's surprising . ( Yoshimura ) I was surprised how many !
( Sato ) They were necessary to show Nobuko 's jealousy .
( Yoshimura ) I was so young ,
and Kei had had his moxibustion treatment
we both had magnificent bodies then .
( Shindo ) Are you still doing it ?
( Sato ) Not anymore . But the clinic 's still there .
I mentioned it on the TV ,
and I still get letters ,
asking me where it is .
( Shindo ) Does it really work ?
( Sato ) If you do it seriously .
You can 't do it half-heartedly ,
it will have the opposite effect .
You have to follow the instructions exactly .
It takes one year .
It won 't work if you give up halfway .
You must be determined to change your condition .
I gained weight , and it felt as if ...
( Shindo ) That 's true for everything .
Not just improving your health .
( Sato ) It felt as if my cells themselves had changed .
( Shindo ) Your cells ? Was your brain the same ?
( Sato ) No , that got worse !
I ate five meals a day .
Mostly rice .
I don 't know why , but rice was easy to digest .
It took four hours to digest completely ,
and so I had to eat every 4 hours .
( Yoshimura ) Even during shooting ? ( Sato ) Yes .
( Yoshimura ) I didn 't notice . ( Shindo ) Not on Onibaba , right ?
( Sato ) That was when we shot Ningen .
If you don 't eat at the right time ,
the treatment will have the opposite effect .
Because of the effect on the intestine
unless food is eaten properly ,
you will get an upset stomach .
It can cause an abnormal gas ,
which can fill the stomach
and cause diarrhoea .
( Yoshimura ) So you ate ... ?
( Sato ) So I had to eat every four hours .
( Shindo ) It was good for us , Kei-san ,
because you lost that civilised look .
( Sato ) If I hadn 't put on weight , I wouldn 't have been hired !
I have moxibustion to thank for that !
( Shindo ) And slowing your brain down was just right for the part !
( Sato ) I was always slow-witted !
( Shindo ) So you became more savage .
( Sato ) I couldn 't get much slower !
( Shindo ) Fundamentally , you are the scientific type .
You had the treatment just in time then .
The swaying grass is very effective .
( Sato ) It 's very effective .
( Yoshimura ) I think I must have run away .
I must have run all the way back to Tokyo .
( Shindo ) We could see the night sky in the distance illuminated by Tokyo .
There was lightning , too .
We all watched it ,
and it made us want to go home back to Tokyo .
But we kept on going .
Hayashi 's music is dynamic .
The mask was made
by a famous mask maker in Kyoto .
We had two made ,
because one needs to be broken later .
The mask maker is dead now , too .
He made us a magnificent mask .
The story is based on The Mask of Flesh story .
The monk , Rennyo , was the 8th Patriarch
of Shin Buddhism .
Until then , the teachings of the sect were not well known ,
so Rennyo set about to change that .
He was a great communicator
and had enormous vitality ,
and , since there was no printing at that time ,
he wrote hundreds of pages
of stories every day to distribute to the people .
One of the stories he wrote was the simple tale , The Mask of Flesh .
A daughter-in-law regularly attended the temple .
Her mother-in-law didn 't like it and tried to stop her ,
by donning a mask to frighten her away from the temple .
The Buddha punished her by making it impossible to remove the mask .
When the daughter-in-law heard what had happened ,
she prayed to the Buddha and the grip of the mask was released .
In those days , daughter-in-laws were often
treated badly by their in-laws .
But they were important to produce the next generation .
Rennyo thought that he could recruit followers by targeting these women .
He wrote the story to warn in-laws
against maltreating their daughters-in-law .
( Sato ) I heard that story when I was young .
I 'm from Aizu in Fukushima .
My parents were in the Nichiren sect , I think .
( Shindo ) It 's a famous Buddhist story .
( Sato ) I heard it from my grandmother .
( Shindo ) The story was actually written
in Yoshizaki in Fukui Prefecture .
The Shin Buddhists were being persecuted by another sect ,
and Rennyo escaped there .
He would return to challenge his persecutors later ,
but while there , he wrote powerful tales ,
such as this one as a means of attracting followers .
It 's easy to understand for farming folk . It 's a simple story .
( Sato ) It was no longer a religious story .
It became a folk tale .
( Shindo ) It 's been handed down over many years ,
because of its simplicity
and its universal human theme of the difficult relationship
between a bride and her mother-in-law .
It resonates to this day .
As for the mask being used
to hide the ugly face of a general ,
that was my idea .
I interpreted the story in a contemporary way .
But that was the original story .
A mother goes to the temple in the evening ,
she listens to the sermon
and falls asleep ,
because the sermon is boring .
The priest knows that ,
and there is a tacit agreement between them .
The priest makes his sermon boring ,
so that the woman can sleep .
She 's tired from her day 's work ,
and comes to the temple
in the evening for a rest .
She can 't leave the children at home ,
so she brings them to the temple , too .
At the temple ,
they are given a sweet bun ,
so the children want to go to the temple to get the bun .
As this is happening , their mother sleeps .
Rennyo 's stories are like this .
He appeals to the people 's instincts .
They are clever stories .
These old folk tales remain ,
because they 're so powerful .
The stories that had no power have long gone .
It was a lot of trouble to make this hole .
The ADs made it .
( Sato ) Yes , I saw them .
( Shindo ) That 's why they weren 't around the set when we were shooting .
But I let them know that they were still
contributing creatively to the film .
Ah , this was the problem cut .
( Yoshimura ) I was shocked when I saw the rushes .
I asked you to cut it .
( Shindo ) It was you who decided to strip off .
( Yoshimura ) No , I was wearing skin-coloured tights ,
and you said they were visible .
You were using a telephoto lens .
I didn 't know anything about the technical side of things ,
I assumed you wouldn 't see from such a distance ,
so I did it in the nude .
When I saw the rushes ,
you could see everything ,
and I asked you to cut it .
I can 't remember how you responded .
I said they wouldn 't be able to show that in the cinemas .
Then I was suddenly nominated
for a Blue Ribbon Award for best supporting actress ,
and I couldn 't say anything more .
( Shindo ) I did cut it a little .
We started shooting
in the morning ,
but it was too muddy to run properly .
We laid boards down to cover the mud
for you to run on .
People were working in mud up to their waists
and chests to solve the problem .
You were inspired by their selfless efforts .
( Yoshimura ) Really ? ( Shindo ) So you stripped off .
( Yoshimura ) Really ? I don 't remember that .
( Shindo ) Really . That was why !
( Yoshimura ) I thought it was because of the tights ,
and because the camera was so far away
and you wouldn 't see .
I thought it was the tights and the camera .
( Sato ) No . I was right behind you .
The camera was over to the left .
You were responding to the way people had worked
up to their chests in the mud .
- You were impressed by that . - ( Yoshimura ) I 'd forgotten .
( Sato ) I remember Shindo-san ,
he was calling out to you
and you stripped off boldly .
We were all impressed .
( Shindo ) It was hard getting that shot .
I thought that shot was going to be easy ,
but it wasn 't .
We put three layers of board down .
The actors waited all morning while we prepared it .
There 's a sequel to this tale .
When we screened the film for Toho ,
Fujimoto cornered me and asked me
what I was going to do about the censors .
I said not to worry ,
but I did end up
cutting it a little bit .
There was never any call for cuts ,
and the few we made settled the matter anyway .
We actually got on well and he helped out
with the film 's distribution .
Incidentally , I received the Fujimoto Award yesterday .
( Yoshimura ) Congratulations !
( Shindo ) I mentioned it because we talked about this story ,
the story of the pubic hair ...
( Yoshimura ) Two friends of mine
saw the film at the theatre and told me
that the scene didn 't look at all obscene .
I was so relieved .
They thought it was good .
( Sato ) Some people who saw the film in the theatre
said they could see my private parts
when I was running .
They must have had good eyesight ,
I was wearing flesh-coloured pants !
It 's not so easy for a man running naked , is it ?
They wouldn 't believe me though .
When it works well , the audience believes it 's real .
( Shindo ) That scene was essential
for the overall atmosphere of the film .
( Yoshimura ) When I saw it , it wasn 't obscene .
It was invigorating .
( Shindo ) That 's down to your refreshing personality ,
your graciousness . Yes . That 's the right expression .
( Sato ) It was about what had been done .
( Shindo ) Yes . We 'd worked hard from the morning .
We 'd been laying the boards ,
and that 's why you did it .
( Yoshimura ) I 'd forgotten .
So it was that everyone had worked so hard ,
and the fact that you could see the tights as well .
( Sato ) He didn 't say anything about tights .
He just called out , " Hey , Jitsuko ! "
And you got the message and stripped off .
I was only 30cm behind you and I remember it .
( Yoshimura ) I thought that it was because ...
you said the tights were visible .
( Shindo ) Anyway , it was good that you were so brave .
It doesn 't look at all lewd .
( Yoshimura ) It 's good that I didn 't think too much about it .
It was only my third film ,
and I didn 't know anything .
In the end , you made it into an invigorating scene .
( Shindo ) You had youth and vitality .
It worked well .
( Yoshimura ) I would have been embarrassed if it was in the studio ,
but there was no one around and the camera was far away .
( Sato ) It was a telephoto lens . ( Yoshimura ) I didn 't know that .
I didn 't know about the camera .
( Shindo ) The telephoto was hard to move around .
But in the end , it was very effective .
Everyone did their bit .
There 's a scene
where Nobuko embraces the tree .
When I took a train from Abiko on the Narita Line ,
I saw this dead pine tree
at the side of the track near one of the stations .
I thought it made an impressive sight ,
and I decided to bring it to the set .
The townspeople were happy to let us take it ,
as it was already dead .
The ADs couldn 't handle it on their own ,
so the lighting and sound crew helped them
to chop it down
and to load it onto a lorry and bring it to the set .
No one complained
about doing that sort of thing .
Everyone mucked in
and no one complained .
Felling and transporting trees is a job for a professional .
People would have been within their rights to refuse ,
but no one did .
There are good and bad sides to it ,
but this kind of group mentality once existed in the Japanese film world .
We had to wait for the sun
to set up here .
You can 't do that sort of thing
unless you have the time .
( Yoshimura ) Nobuko was young then , too .
( Shindo ) She was full of life , too .
It 's seven years now since she died .
( Sato ) Yes , it was 1994 , wasn 't it ?
I met her at the Tennozu Art Sphere theatre just before she died .
They were doing an English play and the director had come over .
Nobuko came to see it .
Togo Haruko was also in the play .
Afterwards I thought
it was as if she had come to say goodbye ,
because she died right after that .
( Shindo ) She was relatively fit up until her death .
She went to the theatre
and to discussion meetings .
( Sato ) It was after The Last Note , wasn 't it ?
( Shindo ) Yes .
( Yoshimura ) She was already sick then , wasn 't she ?
( Shindo ) That 's right .
She was told she had 18 months to live ,
and she did what work she could during that time .
In the end , she ran out of strength .
She didn 't suffer for too long .
The doctors are usually right about cancer .
It was the same for Mizoguchi and Ozu .
They died when the doctors said they would .
You saw where the demon appeared there .
The choreography for that scene was arranged by Kanze Hideo .
It has the feel of a scene from a Noh play .
I wasn 't confident about choreographing that scene ,
so I asked Kanze to help .
You can hear the intense percussion
and the voice yelling .
That 's Kanze 's voice .
( Sato ) Hideo 's voice ? ( Shindo ) Yes .
And what a voice !
It 's astounding !
( Sato ) It would make the window panes vibrate .
( Shindo ) It 's as if a banshee had appeared .
The cry is drawn out ,
leaving a long trail behind it .
( Sato ) It 's a terrifying sound .
( Shindo ) The rapid beat of the drum ,
and then the voice .
Hayashi composed it like that .
Shige did the make-up .
He was famous .
( Yoshimura ) I remember when he went back to Tokyo .
His assistant did Nobuko 's eyebrows ,
but she didn 't like it .
She waited till he came back
to make her up ,
before she would do a scene .
( Shindo ) That 's because he
because he was a veteran .
He made people up based on how they would look on screen ,
not how they looked there and then .
You need experience to do that .
Mind you , he was a difficult person .
He wouldn 't do anything if he didn 't feel like it .
But we worked together well
for a long time .
He would stay on location and make the hair
and the beards and everything .
He would do things like adding that patch of white
to Nobuko 's hair .
( Sato ) It 's fashionable these days .
( Shindo ) It wouldn 't have been any good
if the hair had been completely white .
( Yoshimura ) This is before the typhoon , isn 't it ?
( Shindo ) Yes , we were able to shoot the wind as soon as it arrived ,
because we were there .
It was the same with the birds .
( Yoshimura ) They were ducks and herons , weren 't they ?
( Shindo ) If you 're not living there , you can 't film this kind of thing .
If you have to travel to the location to catch the typhoon ,
you 'll miss it .
If you 're there , you just film it when it happens .
When the wind blew from the south ,
the water level on the north side of the marsh rose by one metre .
That 's because the sea was to the south .
When that happened ,
the prefab we were staying in would often flood .
There were lots of crayfish there and they would come
into the house when the waters rose .
( Yoshimura ) I remember we dug a hole at night
and we would find crayfish in there in the morning .
We 'd take them out and fry them .
( Shindo ) You have to get the mud out of them first .
( Yoshimura ) We caught lots .
( Shindo ) They used to eat crayfish tempura after the war .
( Sato ) There was an elderly couple
who used to go out in a boat on the water .
They would come back
with a bucket full of crayfish .
I assumed that they sold them to the local noodle shop .
( Shindo ) They use them to make soup .
When you 've rinsed the mud off , they 're beautiful .
About the time we finished filming ,
lots of tiny little crayfish hatched out .
This was hard work .
( Sato ) We couldn 't shoot this in the swamp ,
so the ADs had to plant all these reeds .
That was quite a job !
( Shindo ) They were driven to despair at the end .
The wind wouldn 't blow so we used a large fan .
We had to make the wind and create the lightning .
That was tough work .
And it was pouring with rain .
The field was extremely deep ,
and there were plenty of reeds .
What was this fellow 's name ? I can 't remember it ...
( Yoshimura ) That was the end of Hachi .
( Shindo ) They still used this method to make fire
in the countryside when I was a boy .
When they got cold in the fields ,
they would collect pine needles
and use a flint to light the fire .
- Do you smoke , Kei-san ? - ( Sato ) Yes .
( Shindo ) How much ? ( Sato ) A day ?
I 'd say about thirty a day .
Although I cough at the same time !
( Shindo ) Do you need to smoke now ? ( Sato ) No , I 'm fine .
( Shindo ) We had two of these masks made .
I went to Kyoto to order them myself .
I explained the situation
and had them made
at a good price ,
because of the film 's low budget .
( Yoshimura ) It 's an excellent mask . It has such an expression .
It has real expression when Nobuko wears it .
( Shindo ) Kanze Hideo praised it as well .
He tried it on one time
and performed for us .
( Sato ) Do you still have it ? ( Shindo ) Yes , I have it at home .
( Yoshimura ) The perfect one ? ( Shindo ) And the broken one , too .
I took it back and had it joined together again .
The maker was very attached to it , so he fixed it for me .
( Sato ) This was all post-recorded , wasn 't it ?
( Shindo ) That 's right . ( Sato ) The love scenes , too .
And the kisses .
My arms were black and blue
by the time I 'd finished recording .
( Shindo ) You have to get the timing just right .
( Sato ) You said that dubbing the sound would be easier ,
as we could repeat if required .
That 's not what the actors thought .
( Shindo ) Well , I had to persuade you somehow !
I had to get you to do it .
It 's impossible to synchronise things ,
with the grass swaying and the ground below all muddy .
( Sato ) Yes , that 's impossible .
- It was the same with Ningen . - ( Shindo ) Ningen , too , with the sea !
Impossible to synchronise .
( Yoshimura ) You remember so much , Kei-san .
You never fail to impress me .
( Shindo ) The make-up is good here ,
when the mask is stripped off .
The skin looks worn .
( Yoshimura ) Ah , is that Kanze 's voice ? ( Shindo ) That 's right . That 's his yell .
The point here is that , when the film ends ,
we know that Jitsuko leapt across , but we don 't know if Nobuko made it .
Nobody knows .
( Yoshimura ) So I was the only one left ? ( Shindo ) That 's right .